<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration and information of the high and puissant King of Bohemia, against the vniust mandates published in the name of the Emperour as also against those that are further threatned to be decreed and executed, touching the Crowne of Bohemia.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-01</title>
            <author>Bohemia (Kingdom). Sovereign (1619-1620 : Frederick I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838394</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2770</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration and information of the high and puissant King of Bohemia, against the vniust mandates published in the name of the Emperour as also against those that are further threatned to be decreed and executed, touching the Crowne of Bohemia.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-01</title>
                  <author>Bohemia (Kingdom). Sovereign (1619-1620 : Frederick I)</author>
                  <author>Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Jones? or W. Stansby?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Giuen at Prague the 1. of Iuly, 1620.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1848.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:1"/>
            <p>THE DECLARATION AND INFORMATION Of the High and Puiſſant King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> againſt the vniuſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates publiſhed in the name of the Emperour: As alſo againſt thoſe that are further threatned to be decreed and executed, touching the Crowne of BOHEMIA.</p>
            <p>M.D.C.XX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:2"/>
            <head>The Declaration and Information of the high and puiſſant King of BO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMIA, againſt the vniuſt Mandates publiſhed in the name of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; as alſo againſt thoſe that are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther threatned to be decreed and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, touching the Crowne of BO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E, <hi>Fredericke,</hi> by the grace of God, King of Bohemia, Count Palatine of the Rheine, and Prince Elector, Duke of Bauaria, Marquis of Morauia, Duke of Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelburge and Sileſia, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of vpper and lower Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zatia, &amp;c. To all Chriſtian Potentates, Princes Electors, Princes, and States in generall, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them in particular; as alſo to all others of what qualitie, ſtate, or condition ſo euer they be; make knowne our willing ſeruice, friendſhip, and gracious will, giuing them hereby to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that we haue beene certainly and moſt truly informed, in what manner not long ſince, vnder the name of the Emperours Maieſtie, diuers ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, &amp; vnaccuſtomed Mandates and Patents, (to our moſt great preiudice, defamation, and
<pb facs="tcp:2770:3"/> diſhonour) haue beene here and there diſperſed, as well within as without the Empire, and in ſome places publikely ſet vp: Thereby vnder pretence of all manner of vntrue narrations and friuolous ſuggeſtions, pretending, that our true and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Election vnto the Kingdome of Bohemia, made and performed by the generall vnanimous conſent and agreement of the States of the ſaid Kingdome of Bohemia, together with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries thereunto incorporated, is vtterly void, and <hi>de facto,</hi> of no force, or of none effect. And withall affirming, that all the Princes, States, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Empire, (which hitherto out of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian compaſſion, haue in any manner and by any meanes ayded and aſſiſted the oppreſſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of the Kingdome of Bohemia and the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated Countries thereunto annexed, inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſecuted and moleſted by extreame Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Murthers, Robberies, Burnings, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud-ſhedding) are by the ſaid Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Letters Pattents, vpon the auoiding of the actuall declaration and execution of the pains and penalties in that caſe ſet down and appointed by the Imperiall conſtitutions, commanded and ſtrictly enioyned to leaue ayding and aſſiſting of the ſaid greatly perſecuted and oppreſſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſpecially Vs, their now orderly elected and lawfully crowned King. And further, by moſt friuolous vntrue and ſlanderous, imputations againſt vs, and with like ſeuere menacings, by Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb facs="tcp:2770:3"/> power, within a certaine time therein limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet downe; commanding Vs, expreſſely, without any delay, certainly, infallibly and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to abandon, leaue, and giue ouer our ſaid Kingdome of Bohemia, and the Countries incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated thereunto, obtayned by ſo iuſt and lawful a Title, and being in vndeniable iuſt poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Now ſetting apart that, which to the ſlander and diſgrace of the States of Bohemia, hath at large (though vntruly) beene publiſhed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the diſplacing and remoouing of certaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, peruerſe and turbulent Officers, alteration of Gouernment, and eſtabliſhing of Orders for the naturall defence and protection of their Subiects, whereunto by nature they are bound:</p>
            <p>As alſo that, which for the confirmation of the pretended imaginary claime of Inheritance made by the houſe of Auſtria to the ſaid kingdome, may be, and is produced and obiected, out of the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, inſufficient and partiall Declaration made by the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth; concerning the free Election belonging to the Bohemians; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from that vnformal and diſorderly priuate teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication made by King <hi>Vladiſlaus;</hi> and of that out of the Decree, ſeuen and fortie yeares ſince, by fire and ſword compulſiuely extorted and wrung from the aſſembly of the States in Parliament at Prague; together with the ill alleaged obſeruation of their pretended eight hundred yeares ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Sith that all theſe things haue beene fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb facs="tcp:2770:4"/> and confuted by the Apologies and dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarie Declarations made and publiſhed by the ſaid States, with ſuch truth and good ground, as that we thinke it needleſſe here to rehearſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame againe at large.</p>
            <p>Only for the better and plainer iuſtification of our owne Perſon, we ſay that we doubt not, but that all men of indifferent and vnpaſſionate minds, (that haue ſeene and read our Declaration dated the twentieth of October (and ſeuenth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember) publiſhed in Prague, and the Bohemian deduction therein mentioned and ſet downe,) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently perceiue &amp; vnderſtand, vpon what moſt vrgent and ineuitable reaſons and motiues, after ſo great and notorious neceſſities, calamities, and miſeries endured, and thereby inforced defence; the ſaid States of the renowned Kingdome of Bohemia, together with the Prouinces incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to the ſame, haue beene forced and compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto that wel-ordered abdication and reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to them permitted both by the Lawes of God and man, and by vertue of their lawfull priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hitherto inuiolably maintained. And by what occaſion wee for our parts haue beene mooued, and incited to accept of the ſaid vacant Crowne, (vnexpected by vs, and without any thought of Ours) and lawfully caſt vpon vs by a ioynt, free, and generall aſſemblie of the States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Bohemia, according to the ancient Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges and Freedome of Election reſerued vnto
<pb facs="tcp:2770:4"/> them by their fundamentall Lawes. As alſo that in the acceptation thereof wee neuer had any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the further aduancement or increaſing of our owne dignitie, and preſent particular profit, but chiefly and before all things to the glorie of God, the common wel-fare of our natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and as much as poſſibly might bee, to the preſeruation of this famous Kingdome, and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate Principalitie there, by hoſtile power and force almoſt vtterly ſpoyled and ruinated; withall hauing commiſeration and taking pitie vpon the miſeries, ſighes, and lamentable teares which wee had before our eyes of ſo many poore diſtreſſed Chriſtians. And therefore with our pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences we doe now againe teſtifie, that if by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall of this Crowne then offered vnto vs, wee might haue beene a meanes that the deuouring fire of diſſention raiſed in the ſaid Kingdome and the Territories thereof, (and ſtill more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing) might haue beene quenched, the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Religion ceaſſed, their infringed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges reſtored, the Countrey freed and ſecured from menaced bondage and ſuppreſſion, and the Empire alſo, and ſpecially wee our ſelues, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther States bordering about vs, freed from appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant dangers: Wee would not only haue refuſed the acceptation of the ſaid Crowne offered vnto vs, but moſt willingly haue employed our vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeuour in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And wee hope, that no man to whom our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:2770:5"/> and proceedings, from and before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe troubles raiſed in Bohemia, are knowne and made manifeſt, can as well any waies doubt of our ſinceritie, ſeeing it is vndeniable, that we not onely particularly, but ioyntly alſo with other godly and true hearted Princes Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and Princes, preſently vpon their verie firſt burſting out, as vpon the encreaſing of this hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fire, for the preuention of enſuing miſchiefes, haue not ſpared nor refuſed to vſe any good meanes, nor to giue any true and vpright counſell therein. To the which end, at the laſt election day holden in Frankefort, by our fully authoriſed deputies, (together with the aduice and counſell of our fellow temporall Princes Electors) wee did moſt faithfully and diligently labour, and gaue our aduice, to procure, that before wee handled or dealt in any other matter, the hoſtile troubles ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Empire, and ſpecially in the Kingdome of Bohemia, might firſt be brought and reduced to a peaceable and quiet State; for the effecting wherof, we wiſhed &amp; deſired nothing more, then that the Ambaſſadours of the States of Bohemia, then ſent to Frankefort, (which by our deputies was oftentimes moued) at their inſtant requeſt might haue beene admitted and heard, and not (as they were) ſo contemptuouſly reiected and put off.</p>
            <p>And the electorall Records of the laſt procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the ſaid Election at Franckfort, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2770:5"/> That our fully authoriſed deputies were as vnwilling vnto the ſaid contumelious refuſall of the Bohemian Ambaſſadours, as we were readie to the approuing and admiſſion of his Imperiall Maieſtie (as King of Bohemia) into the electorall Colledge; but rather oftentimes haue proteſted and declared, that wee by no meanes would dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any thing from the liberties and rights of the States of the Crowne of Bohemia, nor thereby in any manner ſeeke to prejudice either the one or the other.</p>
            <p>Therefore, becauſe ſuch good and faithfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, aduice, and proteſtations could take no effect, but to the contrarie, the ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of the States of Bohemia (againſt their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient nationall Lawes and Priuiledges) were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained with great diſgrace to goe home againe vnheard; their propoſitions ſet downe in writing, not propounded nor read in the Electorall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor yet the cauſe orderly and lawfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed and handled, (the Countrie in the meane time being ſo grieuouſly afflicted, by continuall and moſt extreame hoſtilitie and deuaſtation) as the like hath not beene heard of:</p>
            <p>So that the interpoſition then made and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the electorall Colledge (which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding required much time, and in the meane while the Kingdome of Bohemia might haue beene vtterly ſpoyled and ouerthrowne) could not be brought to any effectuall treatie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:2770:6"/> was by the contrary part earneſtly, nor with befitting zeale eſteemed of, nor conſidered vpon, as conueniently it ought to haue beene; but much rather, purpoſely the buſineſſe was delayed, that ſo in the meane time the Countrie might bee weakned and tyred out.</p>
            <p>For theſe conſiderations, the States at that time aſſembled together in the Citie of Prague, beeing then in danger of falling into moſt great extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and diſtreſſe, as alſo deſpayring of any equall and impartiall redreſſe of that the contumelious reiection and refuſall of their ſaid Ambaſſadours; were conſtrayned and forcibly compelled, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſome other meanes (by vertue of their ancient and legall priuiledges) and to proceede to the lawfull alteration of the Crowne, as it is now knowne vnto the World: thereby to preſerue and ſaue themſelues from vtter ruine and final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, as by their publique Apologies and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions ſet forth, and imprinted, doth ſufficiently and at large appeare.</p>
            <p>From whence all men, yea alſo euerie ſimple man, may eaſily know and perceiue, That the cauſes and motiues, whereby the States of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, and the Prouinces thereinto incorporated, were enforced to this finall reſolution, are not in any manner to be aſcribed vnto vs, whoſe care and indeuour ſtill was imployed by all the meanes that could be, to procure that peace, quietneſſe, and concord, might be againe reduced, and re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:2770:6"/> within the holy Empire; as alſo, that in the ſaid Kingdome of Bohemia (as a ſpeciall and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Electorall Principalitie) the troubles rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and begun, might be appeaſed, and the ſame reduced to a peaceable and quiet State: But much rather vnto thoſe, who at the verie beginning, (preferring force of armes before friendly means) at the aforeſaid Electorall day, neglected, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected all good counſell, admonition, and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſeeking all the meanes and waies they could, to aduance and effect that their ſo long before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated intent and ſecret meaning.</p>
            <p>And the proceſſe of theſe affaires manifeſtly ſhew, how little the contrarie part is and hath bin inclined to any peaceable courſe of proceeding, as their actions ſufficiently teſtifie; and eſpecially hereby, in that we (at the beginning of our Regall gouernement) when occaſion was motioned of entering into a peaceable treatie, willingly offered to yeeld thereunto. The ſame was notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by them vtterly refuſed and reiected.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is imputed vnto vs, as if wee by our accepting and taking of the Crowne offered vnto vs, both orderly, and without all intruſion, and (according to the ancient Lawes and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Ordinances of the Kingdome of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, and their olde cuſtomes) by lawfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent abdication altogether free and vacant) ſhould thereby rebelliouſly &amp; by force of armes, haue, of our owne actuall manner, vndertaken to
<pb facs="tcp:2770:7"/> pull away the ſaid Kingdome and Prouinces incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated vnto the ſame, from his Imperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, contrarie to the common peace of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: therein we finde our ſelfe to be altogether ouer much wronged, and may in regard thereof, vndergoe and ſtand vnto the cenſure of all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perſons, both within and without the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. For ſeeing that by the fore-mentioned ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall publiſhed deductorie Writings of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Bohemian States, not onely their right and lawfull cauſes of vndertaken Reiection, but alſo their anciently deſcended, &amp; well grounded law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Right of free Election: and that no man with equitie, nor vpon any good ground or ſolid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and iuſt foundation, can boaſt of any lawfull ſucceſſion to the ſaid Realme; much leſſe by dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conuentions, ceſſations, and tranſports (wholly oppoſite to the Fundamentall Lawes) made againſt and without the knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the ſaid States, tranſport the often foreſaid Kingdome of Bohemia, and proprietie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and other the noble Countries, vnto any out-landiſh ſtrangers:</p>
            <p>That all men may ſufficiently perceiue what great wrong and iniuſtice is offered thereby vnto vs, by proceeding againſt vs in ſuch manner, who neuer ſought nor deſired to wrong any one, nor take away againſt right from any man (of how meane eſtate ſoeuer he were) any thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed vnto him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:7"/>
            <p>And although the Emperours Maieſtie within a ſhort time after our Coronation, in an edict pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed before this latter <hi>Mandate,</hi> by diuers colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable circumſtances and allegations, hath taken vpon him, not onely to contradict, but altogether to annihilate and make void the aforeſaid Reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Election, and Coronation made, &amp; conferred vpon vs by the ſaid States of the Crowne of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia: Wee doubt not, but that euery man may eaſily iudge, and diſcerne that his Maieſtie, (who in this cauſe touching the ſaide States of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miaes Abdication or Reiection, and therupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Election and Coronation, preſumeth vpon certaine ſuppoſitions, and pretences of the houſe of Auſtria, being but a partie plaintife) is not for himſelfe to iudge, whether the States of Bohemia haue herein done lawfully, and according to their ancient Lawes and priuiledges; and ſo whether the new Election be in force, and of ſufficiencie, or not: nor can he be warranted by any Law, or vnder any colour of abſolute Imperial authority, power, and Soueraigntie, to aduance and preſſe thorow the priuate deſſignes and particular Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian pretences, with peremptory proceſſe of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, &amp; by his own power to make himſelf iudge in his own cauſe, contrarie to all the Laws &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Empire; no more then the deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Emperours <hi>Frederick, Charles, Rodulph,</hi> and others, in their owne particular controuerſies, and pretences againſt any of the States of the Empire,
<pb facs="tcp:2770:8"/> did euer vndertake and aſſume vnto themſelues, to be both Iudges and parties.</p>
            <p>Beſides this; The States of the Crowne of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, and the prouinces incorporated to the ſame, acknowledge not any iuriſdiction or Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie in the Emperor, in or ouer the Kingdome, (excepting that which concerneth the Feudarie Lands had from the holy Empire) becauſe they are not ſubiect to the Romaine Emperour, nor to any of the holy Empires cenſurers,<note place="margin">Note this well.</note> either at the Imperiall Court, nor in the Chamber at Spires; nor alſo to any other conſtitutions of the Empire, nor Aſſemblings and common decidings, decrees, Tracts, and deciſions of the Empire, but haue their owne ancient Countrie Lawes, Priuiledges, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Exemptions, and Cuſtomes, whereby they are gouerned.</p>
            <p>Whereby it eaſily appeareth, how vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and without reaſon, the Emperours priuie Councell in this priuate buſineſſe arrogate againſt vs vnto themſelues the office of Iudges, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in regard of their Perſons or Qualities they are not called; nor by the temporall Princes Electors, and other Princes, are acknowledged or deemed to be ſuch as are worthie, of their owne authoritie to aſſume ſuch Princes power, as by ſuch vnfit and diſordered proces, of no force nor validitie, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede againſt a King, and a Prince Elector.</p>
            <p>But if his Imperiall Maieſtie, as Archduke of Auſtria, be reſolued orderly and by due courſe of
<pb facs="tcp:2770:8"/> Law to proſecute and produce his pretended heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie claime to the Crowne of Bohemia, then he ought not to doe it before his owne priuie Councel and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,<note place="margin">A poynt verie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable.</note> but (according to the Lawes and Priuiledges of the Crowne of Bohemia) before their owne Iudges, vnto whom ſuch high and weightie cauſes doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine, and muſt as plaintife and actor <hi>Forum rei,</hi> ſue and follow the ſame, before them, and according to the Ordinances of the generall Common Law: as on the other ſide, if as Emperour of Rome, hee be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by order of Law, by any other, according to the golden Bull of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, hee ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, plead, and anſwer before a Palſgraue &amp; Prince Elector; and therefore neither can nor ought to be his owne Iudge. As now it is to be hoped, that no impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall perſon whatſoeuer may any waies doubt of the inſufficiencie and manifeſt nullitie of the aforeſaide pretended Imperiall Edict of caſſation: So likewiſe, we are fully perſwaded, that from the ſame or the like grounds, no man will nor can, but hold and eſteeme the alreadie thereupon enſued Imperiall rigorous mandates; as alſo all ſuch others which are threatned, as may hereafter follow, and be made againſt vs, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, either belonging vnto vs, or aiding of vs; to bee void and of none effect (as in verie truth of themſelues they are) and which we (as occaſion ſerueth, and our neceſſitie requireth) are determined in all euents as is lawfully permitted vnto vs, to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; repugne; in as much as the ſaid proceedings deriued from a paſſionate minde, and concerning his owne priuate pretended right, are done without any lawfull exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb facs="tcp:2770:9"/> or knowledge of the cauſe, and then ſpecially when his Maieſtie hath alreadie hitherto choſen ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe by force of armes, and therein hath not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any kind of hoſtilitie whatſoeuer; &amp; whereby he hath directly not onely proceeded contrarie to the common Lawes of all Nations, but alſo againſt the good and profitable Conſtitutions of the Empire, and the Sacred corporall Oath ratified by Imperiall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation, whereunto his Maieſtie alſo hath bound and obliged himſelfe, in theſe words following:</p>
            <p>That neither he, nor any other for him, or in his name or behalfe, will or ſhall, by violence or force, moleſt or trouble any of the Princes Electors, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prelates, Earles, Barons, nor other States of the Empire, in any manner: But that, if his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie himſelfe, or any other particular perſon, hath right or cauſe to demand or ſue for any thing of them all in generall, or of any of them in particular (for the auoyding and preuenting of all diſſentions, troubles, and other inconueniences in the Empire, thereby to preſerue and maintaine peace and vnitie) he will and ſhall proceede by lawfull order and proceſſe; and in ſuch caſes, where hee or they may haue iuſtice by Law, be willing to ſubmit themſelues thereunto: and will by no meanes, nor vnder any pretence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, permit nor ſuffer them to be moleſted, hurt, or inuaded by warre, burning, defiances, or any other manner of hoſtilitie whatſoeuer. That his Maieſtie alſo ſhall foreſee, and hereafter by no meanes ſuffer nor permit, that any of the States, of high or low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, Princes Electors, Princes, or any others, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2770:9"/> without iuſt cauſe and lawfull audience, wrongfully be proclaimed or declared guiltie of proſcription and baniſhment: But that all caſes ſhall bee proceeded in according to the ordinarie proceſſe, and the holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empires Lawes eſtabliſhed, to the direction of the Lawes of the holy Empire, and the reformed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der held in the Imperiall Chamber, and agreeably be fully and ſtrictly obſerued and followed.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, that his Maieſtie (contrary to the golden Bull, and other Lawes and Ordinances of the holy Empire) ſhall not in any manner, nor by any meanes, of his owne authoritie, ſend out any Reſcript, Mandate, or other preiudiciall Commiſſion, nor by way of entreatie procure the ſame from any other magiſtrate whatſoeuer: with this expreſſe clauſe, That if any thing repugnant to the aforeſaid Articles and ſpeciall points, be either obtained, or ſent forth, that the ſame ſhall be in all reſpects wholly fruſtrate, void, and of no force at all.</p>
            <p>As therefore in this preſent difference, wherein We now are at controuerſie with the Emperous Maieſtie, concerning the priuate particular pretence which hee maketh (as Archduke of Auſtria) vnto our lawfully poſſeſſed Kingdome of Bohemia, and the Prouinces incorporated thereunto, We are not as yet at all ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by ordinarie courſe of Law, to appeare, which We are readie and willing to doe and performe, ſo it be in an indifferent and conuenient place, and before vnpartiall Iudges (according to the priuiledges of Bohemia:) So no man can nor ought to think hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Vs, for refuſing to obey the Imperiall Monitorie
<pb facs="tcp:2770:10"/> Mandate, publiſhed and ſent forth againſt Vs, bearing date the 30. of Aprill laſt paſt; as being wholly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and contrarie to all the Lawes and Ordinances of the Empire, and which alſo is by vertue of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Imperiall Capitulation, and the golden Bull, of it ſelfe fruſtrate, void, and of none effect at all.</p>
            <p>And Wee alſo hope, that other States and fellow-members of the Empire (that haue not as yet openly ſubmitted themſelues vnto the Spaniſh ſeruitude, or that haue not betaken themſelues vnto the ſeruice of that Houſe,) wil not be moued by the ſaid Imperiall Mandate to them directed (which for the reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid is of no force) to deſiſt from their moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable intents and purpoſes, which hitherto they haue had, for the glorie of God, and the comfort and conſolation of ſo many poore Chriſtians wrongfully oppreſſed. And the rather, for that we are perſwaded no man of vnderſtanding that is not led by vntimely immoderate affection, or blinded with priuate conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations &amp; imaginarie reſpects, can iudge or cenſure, that Wee or Our aſſiſtants haue in the leaſt reſpect done any thing contrarie to the Conſtitutions of the Empire, by means of this our firme reſolution, which We haue bin, and are forced to take againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Maieſtie; not as he is Romane Emperour, (for in that reſpect We neither doe, nor will derogate any thing from him, but rather, according to the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Lawes, in all things duely honour and reſpect him) but as Archduke of Auſtria, in regard of his pretended particular and priuate pretences. And therefore, that neither by law nor equitie doe the penalties ſet down
<pb facs="tcp:2770:10"/> in the ſaid actuall peremptorie menacing Declaration and Execution, (as grounded vpon the Conſtitutions of the Empire) belong vnto Vs, and ſo much the leſſe, ſeeing they pretend, that the hitherunto attempted &amp; the hereafter further threatned proceſſe, is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Empires Conſtitutions, which yet are not by Vs at all: but much rather by them of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, cleane laid aſide, and wholly neglected; yea, and in ſuch manner ſo ouerſtridden and tranſgreſſed, and with ſuch vnheard of cruell inſolencies, by the forraigne barbarous ſouldiers who are brought in; as that the inforced Defence and Deliuerance permitted by all Lawes Naturall and Nationall, neither can nor ought by any the like ſurmiſe and colour of Lawe, or other pretended ground of Reaſon whatſoeuer, be drawne and taken at all away from the oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>And if yet his Imperiall Maieſtie (beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation) ſhall ſtill ſuffer himſelfe to be ſo far tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and carried away, as that (not regarding nor reſpecting the precious Oath he hath taken) in reſpect of the claim he pretends (againſt Vs) to Our Crowne of Bohemia, and the Prouinces thereunto incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; continually to moleſt and grieue Vs, our friends, and Allies, with intimated proceſſe of Proſcription <hi>(ex authoritate propria)</hi> and of himſelfe actually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede ſo farre, eſpecially as in hoſtile manner, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade our hereditarie Countries and Territories, and by that meanes (as he hath already done, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth to doe, both in the Kingdome of Bohemia, and the neighbouring confines thereof) occaſion new commotions, diſtractions, diuiſions, and alterations in
<pb facs="tcp:2770:11"/> other places of the Empire, and thereby (as much as in him lyeth) ſeeke to ſubuert &amp; ouerthrow the publike peace of the ſaid Empire: We muſt indeed then with patience commit our Cauſe vnto God the higheſt Iudge, with aſſured confidence, that as hitherto Wee haue palpably felt and ſeene his great and wonderfull prouidence, and mightie out-ſtretched arme extended towards Vs, ſo We hope that his diuine Omnipotence will alſo not hereafter forſake nor abandon Vs, but fatherly affoord vnto Vs ſuch meanes, that, by his powerfull aſſiſtance, We may be able to defend Our ſelfe and Our right, againſt ſo vnlawfull wrongs, and vnexpected barbarous attempts. And hereby We doe expreſſely and in the beſt manner that Wee may or can, truly proteſt, both before God and man, that if, by further menacings, and vnlawfull ſeuere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of Execution, a generall fire of wars (which our good GOD graciouſly auert) ſhall be kindled in Our natiue Countrie of Germanie (as is to be feared) that then the calamities and miſeries that thereby may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, ſhall not in any wiſe be laid vpon, nor imputed vnto Vs; but vnto thoſe Counſellors, and Seruants, that haue not onely neglected to put his Imperiall Maieſtie in remembrance of the Capitulation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Hee hath ſworne (as by duty they were bound) but alſo for their owne benefit, particular commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and imaginarie greatneſſe in the Countrie of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, and out of a reuengefull deſire, haue miniſtred ſuch means as in many particulars are directly againſt the aforeſaid Capitulation, and the common peace and tranquillitie of the whole Countrie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:11"/>
            <p>And this We thought expedient (as alſo our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie requireth) to giue notice of vnto euerie one; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hoping, that no man (who fauoureth reaſon, truth, and equitie) vpon the ſight of this Our moſt true Information, can or will bee moued to cenſure badly of Vs, or to diſtaſte Our Actions, in regard of his Maieſties friuolous Mandate (repugnant to Lawe and the Imperiall Capitulation) publiſhed and ſent forth againſt Vs, Our friends, Allies, and adherents, in regard of this controuerſie that Wee haue with his Maieſtie, as Archduke of Auſtria: nor ſuffer any taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards the performance of the execution of ſuch priuat pretences, to be laid or louied vpon them; which the Houſe of Auſtria it ſelfe, did neuer hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſpect nor account of, nor yet euer did any thing or contributed in the like caſes of Execution, but did euer, and vpon all occaſions, wholly exempt and free themſelues from the ſame.</p>
            <p>In regard whereof, the Princes Electors, Princes, and States of the Empire, at this time, haue leſſe cauſe to trouble and to burthen themſelues therewith on the behalfe of the ſaid Houſe of Auſtria, againſt Vs; but on the contrarie, to be readie and willing, if We or Ours, in manner aforeſaid, ſhall be aſſaulted and inuaded, to aide and aſſiſt Vs with their aduice and meanes, and according to the Order of Executions, (which Wee euer, and at all times, haue duely reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and obſerued;) and ſo much the rather, to afford Vs their helpe, for that euery particular Grant, Tract, and State of the Empire, ought, and is reciprocally
<pb facs="tcp:2770:12"/> bound to aide and aſſiſt each other, in the like hoſtile oppreſſion and inuaſion. To the which, hereby Wee moſt friendly, louingly, and graciouſly incite them, with promiſe when occaſion ſhall bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to requite them with the like.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Prague</hi> 
                  <date>the 1. of Iuly, 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2770:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
